Guide to the Library of Information Pamphlets, 1938-1946
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Library of Information Pamphlets
1938-1946
United States. Office of Education. School and College Civilian Morale Service. Vassar College Key Center of Information and Training
4.5 cubic feet (6 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Pamphlets, reports, clippings, and other printed materials relating to the Second World War.
Administrative History
During World War II, the U.S. Office of Education designated colleges throughout the country to serve as "Key Centers" that would make available to people of their surrounding areas information concerning the war and related issues. In doing so, each Key Center of Information and Training performed a war service to promote civilian morale. Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, NY, was one of 11 colleges in New York State, outside New York City, chosen to serve as a Key Center. With assistance from the Office of Education's Civilian Morale Service, Vassar maintained a "Library of Information" which consisted of pamphlets and printed materials from both government and private sources. Though not officially part of the Vassar Library, the Library of Information was housed in its central hall and maintained under the direction of librarian Dorothy Plum.
Scope and Content Note
Pamphlets and other printed materials issued by the U.S. Office of Education's Civilian Morale Service and distributed by the Key Center of Information and Training at Vassar College. The materials address a variety of topics pertaining to World War II and related issues, including the geographical theaters of the war, military recruitment, wartime production, and civilian morale.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Summary of reports of the New York State Key Centers of Information and Training to June 15, 1942.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
World War, 1939-1945--Air operations; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations; World War, 1939-1945--Occupied territories; World War, 1939-1945--United States
Document Types:
Clippings (information artifacts); Newspapers; Pamphlets; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
War and War Crimes; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, March 2022. Updated June 2022.
Updated by Emma Gronbeck, February 2025.
Container List
- Card Index to Library of Information Pamphlets (incomplete), undated (Box 6)
- Aeronautic Education, 1940-1943; (6 items) (Box 1)
- Africa, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Air Raids - Protective Measures, 1942-1943; (7 items) (Box 1)
- Airplanes, 1942-1943; (4 items) (Box 1)
- Alaska, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Aliens, 1942; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Asia, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Australia, 1939-1945; (10 items) (Box 1)
- Baltic States, 1944; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Belgian Congo, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Belgium, 1945; (8 items) (Box 1)
- Brazil, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Business, 1941; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Burma, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Campaigns, Aerial, 1941-1945; (4 items) (Box 1)
- Campaigns, Africa, 1942-1943; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Campaigns, France, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Campaigns, Greece, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Canada, 1941-1946; (16 items) (Box 1)
- Censorship, 1943; (3 items) (Box 1)
- Chemical Warfare, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Child Labor, 1942; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Child Psychology, 1942-1943; (3 items) (Box 1)
- Child Welfare, 1942-1945; (6 items) (Box 1)
- China, 1942-1943; (7 items) (Box 1)
- Churchill, Winston, 1942-1944; (27 items) (Box 1)
- Civilian Defense, 1940-1941; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Civilian Defense, 1942; (19 items) (Box 1)
- Civilian Defense, 1943; (8 items) (Box 1)
- Civilian Defense, 1944, undated; (4 items) (Box 1)
- Colleges and Universities, 1940-1942; (11 items) (Box 1)
- Colleges and Universities, 1943; (7 items) (Box 1)
- Conscientious Objectors, 1942-1943; (3 items) (Box 1)
- Conservation of Resources, 1941; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Czechoslovakia, 1941-1944; (21 items) (Box 1)
- Democracy, 1940-1943; (13 items) (Box 1)
- Denmark, 1943; (7 items) (Box 1)
- Dodecanese Islands, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Dutch West Indies, 1944; (1 item) (Box 1)
- East (Far East), 1942; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Education, 1941-1944; (4 items) (Box 1)
- Education, Australia, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Education, China, 1943-1944; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Education, Europe, 1943; (2 items) (Box 1)
- Education, Netherlands, 1942; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Education, Russia, 1943; (1 item) (Box 1)
- Family Security, 1941-1942; (5 items) (Box 2)
- Finland, 1942; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Flags, U.S., 1944; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Food, 1943; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Forums, Open, 1939-1943; (4 items) (Box 2)
- France, 194201945; (5 items) (Box 2)
- Gardens, 1942-1943; (4 items) (Box 2)
- Germany, 1940-1943; (8 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, 1939-1944; (16 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Armed Forces, 1943-1945; (3 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Army, 1941-1944; (5 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Empire, 1942-1944; (5 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Navy, 1942-1945; (7 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Royal Air Force, 1940-1945; (7 items) (Box 2)
- Great Britain, Social Conditions, 1942; (2 items) (Box 2)
- Health, 1942-1943; (12 items) (Box 2)
- High School Victory Corps, 1942-1943; (3 items) (Box 2)
- Housing, 1942-1944; (6 items) (Box 2)
- India, 1942-1943; (21 items) (Box 2)
- India, 1944-1945; (11 items) (Box 2)
- Inflation, 1942-1945; (5 items) (Box 2)
- International Organization, 1942-1945; (23 items) (Box 2)
- Italy, 1942-1943; (4 items) (Box 2)
- Labor, 1940-1942; (15 items) (Box 2)
- Labor, 1943; (16 items) (Box 2)
- Labor, 1944; (7 items) (Box 2)
- Language Study, 1942, 1944; (2 items) (Box 2)
- Lend-Lease Operations, 1941-1943; (6 items) (Box 2)
- Lend-Lease Operations, 1944-1945; (4 items) (Box 2)
- Levant (Middle East), 1942-1943; (2 items) (Box 2)
- Liberty, 1941-1942; (7 items) (Box 2)
- Libraries, 1942-1944; (10 items) (Box 2)
- Malta, 1943; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Medical Aspects, 1942-1943; (5 items) (Box 2)
- Mental Hygiene, 1943; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Merchant Marine, 1943; (1 item) (Box 2)
- Military Service, Compulsory, 1940-1944; (5 items) (Box 3)
- Military Training, 1941-1942; (3 items) (Box 3)
- Morale, 1941-1944; (9 items) (Box 3)
- National Defense, 1938-1942; (12 items) (Box 3)
- Naval Operations, 1940-1944; (3 items) (Box 3)
- Netherlands, 1943; (1 item) (Box 3)
- New Zealand, 1943-1944; (2 items) (Box 3)
- Norway, 1940-1943; (5 items) (Box 3)
- Nurses and Nursing, 1941-1943; (23 items) (Box 3)
- Patents, 1943; (1 item) (Box 3)
- Peace, 1941-1944; (13 items) (Box 3)
- Philippine Islands, 1943; (1 item) (Box 3)
- Poland, 1941; (7 items) (Box 3)
- Poland, 1942-1944; (16 items) (Box 3)
- Press, 1942; (1 item) (Box 3)
- Prices--Regulation, 1942-1943; (12 items) (Box 3)
- Prices--Regulation, 1944-1945; (11 items) (Box 3)
- Priorities, 1942; (1 item) (Box 3)
- Prisoners and Prisons, 1944; (2 items) (Box 3)
- Propaganda, 1942; (2 items) (Box 3)
- Race Problems, 1942-1943; (2 items) (Box 3)
- Radio Broadcasting, 1942; (1 item) (Box 3)
- Rationing, 1942-1945; (6 items) (Box 3)
- Raw Materials, 1941-1943; (5 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-), 1941; (5 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-), 1942; (16 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-), 1943; (24 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-), 1944; (4 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-)--Economic Aspects, 1941-1943; (14 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-)--Economic Aspects, 1944-1945; (9 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-)--Education, 1941-1944; (9 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-)--Great Britain, 1942-1945; (5 items) (Box 3)
- Reconstruction (World War, 1939-)--U.S., 1940-1944; (11 items) (Box 3)
- Recreation, 1942-1943; (6 items) (Box 3)
- Refugees, 1939-1946; (8 items) (Box 4)
- Religion, 1940-1944; (20 items) (Box 4)
- Rural Schools, 1942; (1 item) (Box 4)
- Russia, 1942-1943; (5 items) (Box 4)
- Salvage, 1942-1943; (7 items) (Box 4)
- Science, 1942-1943; (4 items) (Box 4)
- Schools at War, 1943-1944; (3 items) (Box 4)
- Service Men, Discharged, 1942-1945; (11 items) (Box 4)
- Speakers, 1942-1943; (2 items) (Box 4)
- Technical Literature, 1940-1943; (6 items) (Box 4)
- Transportation, 1941-1943; (10 items) (Box 4)
- United Nations, 1942-1944; (14 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Armed Forces, 1942-1944; (12 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Armed Forces Institute, 1942-1943; (3 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Army, 1942-1943; (10 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Army -- Women's Army Corps, 1942-1944; (4 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Coast Guard, 1942-1943; (2 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1941-1942; (4 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Foreign Relations, 1941-1945; (4 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Marine Corps, 1942-1944; (8 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Maritime Service, 1944; (2 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Navy, 1942-1943; (4 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Navy -- Women's Naval Reserve, 1942; (2 items) (Box 4)
- U.S. Office for Emergency Management, 1942; (1 item) (Box 4)
- Venereal Diseases, 1941-1943; (17 items) (Box 4)
- Vocational Education, 1941-1944; (8 items) (Box 4)
- War Aims, 1941-1943; (7 items) (Box 4)
- War and Children, 1942-1943; (5 items) (Box 4)
- War and Education, 1942-1943; (5 items) (Box 4)
- War Finance, 1942-1945; (20 items) (Box 4)
- War Production, 1941-1942; (15 items) (Box 4)
- War Production, 1943-1944; (8 items) (Box 4)
- West Indies, 1943; (1 item) (Box 4)
- Wilson, Woodrow, 1942; (3 items) (Box 4)
- World War, 1939-, 1941-1942; (8 items) (Box 4)
- World War, 1939-, 1943-1944; (8 items) (Box 4)
- World War, 1939- -- Great Britain, 1939-1945; (18 items) (Box 4)
- World War, 1939- -- Peace, 1941-1945; (24 items) (Box 5)
- World War, 1939- -- U.S., 1940-1942; (8 items) (Box 5)
- World War, 1939- -- U.S., 1942-1945; (15 items) (Box 5)
- Youth, 1940-1944; (12 items) (Box 5)
- Yugoslavia, 1942-1944; (9 items) (Box 5)